# 哈喽 大家好
Hello guys
# 这次我伯爷买了一个白菜
This time my uncle has bought a napa cabbage
# 说让我做个白菜给他吃
He asked me to cook it for him
# 我伯爷说农村的柴火灶炒不出那种效果
But he said that the firewood stove in countryside cannot get the right taste
# 所以让我用这个炒一下
So he wants me to cook with this stove
# 炒个酸辣大白菜
To stir and fry a "Sour-and-Spicy Napa Cabbage"
# 一哈呀 四伯爷这
All in one dish, uncle?
# 一哈嘛
Together
# 一哈炒有点多不多了
Will it not be too much?
# 本来这个白菜我拿回来做成2顿吃的 给你说嘛
I took it back for two meals, (给你说嘛是在说啥?)
# 中间的那个芯芯弄来煮汤
Its stem for cooking soup
# 这个边边就弄来炒来吃
And leaves for stir-frying
# 撕碎点
Smaller pieces
# 大块大块的都可以
It will do with larger ons
# 大块大块的吃起卡喉咙的
Larger pieces would stuck in by throat
# 所以趁人还没老赶紧多学点做点好吃的先吃了再说
So take the time when you are not too old to learn and cook more tasty stuff. Enjoy the food first!
# 我们这个白菜撕出来了
We've just finished preparing the cabbage
# 洗一下 一定要把水份沥干了再炒
Wash it a while. The water has to be completely removed before cooking
# 要不然的话这个里面有水炒出来了水哒哒的
Otherwise with the fluid and water the dish would become too watery
# 水汤汤多得很
Water, fluid, too much in it
# 那跟煮的白菜汤一样
Like napa cabbage soup
# 是
Indeed
# 好 下面准备一点干辣椒
Ok, next prepare some dried chilli pepper
# 剪一点干辣椒
cut a few dried chilli pepepr
# 可以多剪2个嘛
You will cut 2 more, won't you?
# 多剪2个那样子就
2 more then
# 这个海椒不辣
The chilli pepper is not really spicy
# 我们今天用的这个辣椒是子弹头
Today we use the chilli called "Zidantou Chilli Pepper" (lit. bullet-head chilli pepepr)
# 颜色好看 就是辣度的话一般般
It has beautiful colour, but the spicy taste is not very strong
# 辣度就不够
It is not spicy enough
# 好 差不多了
Okay, almsot there
# 够了够了
Enough, enough
# 够了
Good
# 然后再抓几颗青花椒下去
Then grab a few green Sichuan peppercorns
# 可以了嘎
Okay?
# 可以
Ok
# 一般外地人的话就不要加青花椒你们吃不惯的话
Normally if non-local don't really eat green peppercorns you don't need to put them in
# 花椒加进去又小颗一下子就吃到嘴里去
Peppercorns are so small and they slip into your mouth
# 就差不多了嘛
Almost done
# 就是放点蒜 干海椒 花椒 再加白菜
Just some garlic, chilli peppers, peppercorns, and then drop in the napa cabbage
# 要的啊
Good
# 再加点陈醋
And some vinegar
# 要得要得
Nice!
# 要得
Nice
# 可以了 走嘛
Okay, let's go
# 好啦 我们炒这个大白菜啊
Ok, now we stir and fry this napa cabbage
# 一定要把这个锅烧得很烫
You must heat this wok very really scalding (我不太确定用词？
# 然后把油温烧高一点
And keep a higher oil temperature
# 这个火候要掌握好哦
You shall control the heat well
# 啊
Ahm
# 不要像漆二娃那样子炒糊了
Don't overcook it like Qi Erwa
# 蒜
Garlic
# 辣椒
Pepper
# 白菜
and napa cabbage
# 然后开大火
Turn to high heat
# 盐 白糖 陈醋 酱油
Salt, sugar, vinegar, soy sauce
# 吃哈看嘛
I'll have a try
# 尝哈看
help yourself
# 这个黑是加的陈醋的颜色 还有酱油
The dark bit is the colour of vinegar, and soy sauce as well
# 这个不是炒黑的
Not because it's overcooked
# 怎么样
How is it?
# 可以
Nice!
# 我们炒这个白菜就是油稍微多一点
We cook this napa cabbage, it needs a bit more oil
# 然后火大一点
and the heat higher
# 直接翻炒
Head straight to stir-frying
# 炒到8成熟开始调味
When it's 80% cooked, we can start seasoning
# 然后这个盐要比平时炒菜多一些
And use a bit more salt than usual
# 因为加了醋
because of the vinegar
# 醋会抵消一部分的咸味
will counter some taste of salt
# 然后调盐味一定要最后面来
Salt must be added at last
# 如果太早放盐下去这个白菜会出水
If it's put in too early the cabbage fluid would flow out
# 然后就不脆了就软了
And the leaves are not crunchy anymore, they become soft
# 现在我们这个白菜是脆的 很脆
Now our cabbage is, very crunchy
# 好吃
Delicious
# 嗯
Hm
# 我们这个唯一的不好就是油稍微要重一些
The only shortcoming of this dish, the oil is a bit "broad"
# 如果不重的话就不能够开大火
But if you don't have enough oil, you can't get the high heat
# 肯定的撒
Of course
# 油不重开大火炒就要糊
If the oil is not enough, stir-frying in high heat will burn the cabbage
# 不但要糊 那个味道也不好
Not only is it burned, but its taste is spoiled
# 嗯
Um
# 我这次用的火候是用的中大火
I used a medium-high heat this time
# 油的话稍微重一点点
The oil is just a bit "broader"
# 然后前期就是放下去翻炒翻炒
And the first stage is just, drop in the cabbage, stir and fry
# 你不要手软 一定要开大火
Don't be hesitate, the high heat is a must
# 漆二娃炒菜她手上没得力的翻炒都
Qi Erwa's cooking, her arms are not so strong that the stir-frying
# 翻炒都成问题嘎
she has some problems in stir-frying
# 她手脚慢了 所以说有些东西炒久了炒糊了安
She's sometimes less deft, and things are cooked too long and burned
# 嗯
Um
# 酸辣大白菜一定要火够大
Sour-and-Spicy napa cabbage, the heat has to be high enough
# 还有包菜也是跟这个原理差不多
And cabbage, it's the same way
# 就是不能加水 炒白菜记住一定不能焯水
The only thing is, you must not put any water in it. No need to parboil the cabbage when you're gonna stir and fry it
# 焯了水的白菜炒起就是要
Parboiled cabbage in stir-frying dish
# 不好吃
It's just not tasty
# 水咂砸的
watery and mashy
# 水汪汪的跟煮的白菜汤一样
like cabbage stew
# 啊 就是
Ah, indeed
# 好了本期视频就到这里
Okay, that's all for today's video
# 拜拜
Bye!
# 下饭撒 这个
Appetite-arousing, this dish
# 可以
Nice